I would ask this of you as well.
私からも頼む
本字幕由诸神字幕组出品，仅供学习交流
Please help me, together with Daryun.
ダリューンと共に　私を助けてくれ
更多中日双语字幕，尽在www.kamigami.org 及微博@诸神字幕组
I am grateful for your words, but...
ありがたいお言葉ですが…
では　こうしよう
Then, let us do this.
In exchange for your loyalty,
I will compensate you handsomely.
私は　お主の忠誠を求める代わりに　十分な代償を支払う
私がルシタニアを追い払い　パルスの国王になった暁には…
Once I have driven off Lusitania
and I have become the king of Pars,
ナルサス卿　お主を宮廷画家として迎えよう
Lord Narsus, l will appoint you Court Painter.
なっ
I like you!
気に入った
How about it? Did you hear that, Daryun?
どうだ　聞いたか　ダリューン
His Highness's magnanimity as a monarch!
殿下の　この君主としての度量
Your Highness, you would
make Narsus Court Painter?
殿下　ナルサスを宮廷画家になさるなど
It would mean leaving a stain upon
the history of Parsian culture!
パルスの文化史上に　汚点を残すことになりますぞ
That seems acceptable to me.
いいではないか
I would rather have Narsus
paint a living portrait of me,
私は　ルシタニアの高名な画家に　死に顔を描かれるより
than have a famed Lusitanian
artist paint my death portrait.
ナルサスに　生きた姿を描いてもらいたい
However, King Andragoras finds
the very mention of my name offensive.
ですが　私の名は　王の忌諱に触れるところ
This may cause Your Highness
to incur His Majesty's displeasure,
殿下が　ご不興を被ることもありえますが
それでも　よろしいですか
but are you willing to accept that?
Without question.
無論
I understand.
分かりました
このナルサス　アルスラーン殿下に　お仕えいたします
I, Narsus, shall serve you, Prince Arslan.
ありがとう　ナルサス
Thank you, Narsus.
Now that that is settled, let us depart quickly.
そうと決まれば　早々に出立しよう
We must return to the Royal Capital,
to Ecbatana, as soon as possible.
一刻も早く王都に…　エクバターナに戻らねば
ええ　馬と荷の用意をいたしましょう
Yes, let us get our bags
packed and the horses ready.
Yes, sir.
はっ
Oh, also, Elam.
ああ　それと　エラムよ
Sir?
はい
I will have a friend of mine in the
port town of Gilan look after you.
お前は　ギランの港町にいる知人に　預かってもらうことにする
What? Is that...
えっ　それは…
He owns a merchant vessel,
そいつは商船主でな
もし　ルシタニアが侵攻してきても　海上に逃げられるし
so even if Lusitania invades,
you will be able to flee to sea
更に　異国へ渡ることもできる
and even cross to foreign lands.
You should be safe there.
そこなら安全だろう
I do not wish to go.
嫌でございます
I, Elam, owe you a great debt,
このエラム　ナルサス様には一生かけても足りぬほどの大恩がございます
such that I could never repay,
even if I were to spend my entire life!
Please allow me to continue
to accompany you, Lord Narsus!
これからもナルサス様のお供をさせてください
But you are still a child.
しかしな　お前は　まだ子供だ
You needn't go out of your way
to come on this dangerous journey...
わざわざ危険な旅に同行せずとも…
ナルサス様よりは大人です
I am more of an adult than you, Lord Narsus.
Lord Narsus, you are incapable
of doing anything for yourself.
ナルサス様は　一人では　何もできないではありませんか
Laundry, cleaning, acquiring art supplies...
洗濯　掃除　画材の調達
これは　エラムが正しいな
Elam has the right of it there.
Daryun!
ダリューン
Lord Daryun, please keep telling him that.
ダリューン様　もっと言ってください
Narsus, I would ask this of you as well.
ナルサス　私からも頼む
殿下…
Your Highness...
エラムを置いていったとして
If we were to leave Elam behind,
who else among us would be able
to prepare such delicious meals?
我らの中で　こんなに美味な食事を作れる者が　他にいるか
決まりだな
That settles it.
Elam, I look forward to your continued company.
エラムよ　これからも　供を頼む
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございます
では　早速　荷造りをします
Then I will get our bags packed right away.
I must get my things in order as well.
私も　身の回りのものを整えねば
Elam, is there anything I can help with?
エラム　何か手伝うことはあるか
As I said before, Your Highness,
please quietly remain seated.
だから　殿下は黙って座っていてくださいませ
しかし　エラムだけに　任せておくわけには…
But I cannot leave it all just to you.
His Highness never had the chance to make friend
--This is my job.
殿下は宮廷では同年代の友が得られなかったからな
これは私の仕事でございます
--his own age at Court.
--Your Highness need not concern yourself.
殿下はお気になさらず　私だけで　事足ります
--I hope Elam
--I will manage perfectly well on my own.
エラムには　殿下のよい友になってもらいたいものだ
--can become a good friend to His Highness.
--Now, please go take a seat.
さあ　座っていてください
しかし…
But...
パルス暦３２０年　秋
Pars Era, the year 320, autumn.
Prince Arslan only had
the warrior Daryun at his side
戦士ダリューンと共に
when the two of them made good
their escape from the battlefield.
たった二人で戦場より落ち延びた王子アルスラーンは
On this day,
この日　軍師ナルサスと　その小姓エラムを供に加え
he added to his company the
strategist Narsus and his page, Elam,
and took his first step upon a journey
苦難に満ちた旅へ　第一歩を踏み出した
that would be filled
with trials and tribulation.
These aren't my words
日听&翻译
小伍
sora
兰樱
校对
小江
mam
If the whole world only had left hands
时间轴
电池雪糕
压制
Coolkid
Don't be the bastards who hide their right hands
There's nothing beyond this azure
The day I realized that,
I stopped looking up at the sky
And in the bottomless swamp,
look, there's a bottom
In this town that's growing
even more tainted even now
Even if you just tried to breathe the air
You'd end up breathing in the bad stuff, too
And in the bottomless swamp,
look, there's a bottom
In this town that's growing
even more tainted even now
Even if you just tried to breathe the air
You are friend, Baby Dream
Before I knew it, my heart
Was full of things I had to love all the way
Always losing, leaving
Even the unbearable stuff
Because I don't want to live my days
lamenting, unable to keep them safe
You are friend, Baby, Dream
I'll grow even stronger
These aren't my words
But our words
The horses...
馬…　俺たちの馬がいないぞ
Our horses are gone!
Curse you...
おのれ…　逃げられると思うなよ
Do not think you can escape!
The path down the mountain
山から下りる道は　すでに我らの仲間に　固められておるわ
has already been secured by our comrades!
They went down the mountain on foot.
ヤツら徒歩で山を下りていきました
How arduous for them.
ご苦労なことだ
On foot, they are unlikely to
reach the bottom by day's end.
徒歩では　今日中に麓へは着けぬだろう
I hope they do not run into any bears or wolves.
熊や狼に出会わなければよいがな
Your Highness.
殿下
What is on your mind?
何をお考えで
王都は　まだ無事だろうか
Do you suppose the Royal Capital is still safe?
I understand your impatience,
but please restrain yourself.
焦る気持ちは分かりますが　抑えてください
Were we to descend the mountain immediately,
今すぐ山を下りれば　カーラーンとの戦いは避けられません
a fight with Kharlan would be unavoidable.
We will confine ourselves to this
cave for a while to wait them out.
しばらく　この洞窟にこもり　やり過ごします
その間に敵の包囲網を逆用する道を考えましょう
In the meantime, let us think of a way
to turn their encirclement to our own advantage.
How do we do that?
どのように
We make the enemy focus their
manpower where we wish them to.
自分たちの望む場所に　敵の兵力を集中させる
That is the first step in any strategy.
それが　まず　戦法というものの第一歩です
いかに武勇があろうとも
No matter how great your military prowess,
the value of strategy is in
securing victory before you exhaust it.
それを使いきる前に勝利を収めることが　戦法の価値です
ダリューンは私のために　大軍の中を突破してくれたが
But Daryun broke through a
massive army to come for me.
That is one man's valor.
あれは個人の勇です
Brave warriors such as
Daryun are one in a thousand.
ダリューンのような勇者は１０００人に１人
軍の指揮者たる者は　最も弱い兵士を基準として
The commander of an army
must think of his weakest
soldier as the standard
and still emerge victorious.
それでも　勝たなければなりません
This holds doubly true for
the monarch of a kingdom,
ましてや　一国の王ともなれば
最も無能な指揮者でも　敵軍に負けぬよう　方策を巡らすべきなのです
who ought to devise his plans,
so that even his most incompetent
commander will not be defeated.
なんだ
What is it?
Nothing. Continue.
いや　続けてくれ
兵の強さに溺れて　戦法を軽んじたとき
When he is too sure of the strength
of his men and neglects strategy...
If matters should go awry at some point...
一度　事態が狂えば　どうなるかは
殿下ご自身が　アトロパテネで　ご経験なさったことでしょう
I am sure Your Highness experienced
the result for yourself at Atropatene.
King Andragoras never knew defeat.
アンドラゴラス王は　敗北を知らぬお方でした
That self-conceit gave rise to the
king who was uninterested in politics.
その自負が
なんでも戦いで解決しようとする政治に無関心な王を生み出してしまったのです
The king who tried to
resolve all matters with war.
If it is your will that you would be
your father's successor in that sense,
あなたが　そのような意味において
お父上の後継者たらんと思われるのであれば
I will abandon my post as
Court Painter at a moment's notice,
私は　いつでも　宮廷画家の地位を捨てますぞ　アルスラーン殿下
Prince Arslan.
Yes, I will take your words to heart.
肝に銘じておく
Daryun, even if you come
upon Kharlan, do not kill him.
ダリューン　カーラーンに出くわしても殺すなよ
There is no doubt that he knows
something that is beyond belief.
ヤツは何やら途方もないことを知っているに違いない
I know.
分かっている
途方もないこと
Something beyond belief?
But as for what that might be,
ただ　それが何事であるのやら　今のところ　まるで見当もつきません
I cannot even begin to guess right now.
Circumstances have led me to this.
故あってのことです
O sad and pitiable prince,
you have done no wrong.
悲しく　あわれな王子よ
あなたは　何も悪くない
You have done no wrong,
but I would have you die here.
悪くはないが…
ここで死んでいただこう
Something beyond belief...
途方もないこと…
Azrael...
アズライール
Were you not supposed to be
gone to accompany Prince Arslan?
お主　アルスラーン殿下のお供に　行っていたはずでは
キシュワード様
Lord Kishward!
ここにおいででしたか
This is where you were!
What is it?
何事だ
Kishward!
キシュワード
Lord Bahman.
バフマン殿
What is the matter?
どうなされました
今し方　アトロパテネから　早馬が
A mounted courier arrived
from Atropatene just moments ago!
"Cavalry Captain, Kingdom of Pars
Bahman"
Has something happened?
何かあったのですか
我がパルス軍が大敗し　アンドラゴラス陛下は　行方不明に
Our Parsian army suffered a crushing defeat
and King Andragoras has gone missing!
And the Lusitanian army is closing in
ルシタニア軍は　王都エクバターナの城外まで迫っていると
on the walls of the Royal Capital of Ecbatana!
We're surrounded by Lusitanian soldiers?!
ルシタニア兵に囲まれてるって
What happened at Atropatene?
アトロパテネで　何があったんだよ
Did the Parsian army lose?
パルス軍が負けたのか
King Andragoras would never lose.
アンドラゴラス王が負けるわけがない
But they say that Lusitania has us surrounded...
でもルシタニアに囲まれてるって…
Probably a lie.
うそだろ
王はどこにいるの
Where is the King?
Are we going to be all right?
俺たち大丈夫なのか
The walls of Ecbatana will never fall.
エクバターナの城壁が破れるものか
なんだ
What's that?
Th-There!
あ…あれ
That is...
あれは…
Lord Shapur!
"Cavalry Captain, Kingdom of Pars
Shapur"
シャプール殿
What?!
なんだと　マルズバーンのシャプール様が…
Lord Shapur, the Marzbān, has been...
Hear me!
聞け
You heathens within the
walls who do not fear God!
城中の神を畏れぬ異教徒どもよ
I am a man of the cloth,
わしは唯一絶対の神イアルダボートにお仕えする聖職者
who serves the one and only
absolute God of Yaldabaoth!
I am Bodin, the Archpriest and Inquisitor!
"Archpriest of the Faith of Yaldaboath
Bodin"
大司祭にして異端審問官　ボダンである
今この異教徒の肉体をもって　貴様らに神のご意思を伝えよう
Using the body of this heathen here,
we will convey God's will to you!
まず　こやつの左足の小指を斬り落とす
First, we will cut off the
little toe of his left foot!
Then, on to his fourth toe, his middle toe...
次いで　薬指　中指
左足が終わったら　次は右足
When we finish his left foot,
next, his right foot!
And then, next, his hands!
更に　次は手だ
We will show you heathens within the walls
神に逆らう者の末路を　城内の異教徒どもに思い知らせてやろうぞ
the fate that befalls those who defy God!
You animal!
この　けだもの
You're a brute with no respect for warriors!
戦士に敬意を払わぬ畜生が
You savages worship an evil god!
邪神を信仰する蛮族め
シャプール様を汚すな
Don't you dare dishonor Lord Shapur!
This man is an apostle of evil,
who refuses to worship our god!
この男は我らが神をあがめぬ悪魔の使徒
A cursed beast!
呪われし　けだものだ
Mercy for a heathen is not...
異教徒に慈悲を与えるなど…
A bastard like you...
貴様などに…
There is no reason I should have to listen
to a bastard like you censure my beliefs.
貴様などに　俺の信仰を　云々されるいわれはない
Hurry up and kill me.
さっさと殺せ
貴様の神に救われるくらいなら
I would rather go to hell or anywhere
else than be saved by your god.
俺は地獄へでも　どこへでも　行ってやる
And from there, I will watch to the bitter end
そして　そこから　貴様らの神と国とが
as your god and your
kingdom are devoured and killed
己ら自身の残忍さに食い殺されるのを…
見届けてやるわ
by your own cruel ways.
Why you... sinful rat!
この…　罰当たりめ
異教徒め
You heathen!
You beast!
けだものめ
神の敵め
You enemy of God!
思い知ったか
Have you learned your lesson now?!
エクバターナの人々よ　俺を矢で射殺してくれ
People of Ecbatana,
shoot me to death with an arrow!
It is too late to save me!
どうせ　俺は助からぬ
Rather than be tortured to death
by these Lusitanian savages,
ルシタニアの蛮人に　なぶり殺されるより
I would die by the arrow of a friend!
味方の矢で死にたい
黙れ
Shut up!
No arrow will reach you at this distance!
この距離で矢など届くか
シャプール様
Lord Shapur!
Save Lord Shapur!
シャプール様を助けろ
あの狂信者を狙え
Aim for that zealot!
Stop that!
The fools.
バカめ　この距離で矢など届くか
No arrow will reach at this distance!
Come! Come! Shoot some more!
ほれほれ　もっと射ってこい
大司祭様　お下がりください
Lord Archpriest, please get back.
あの城壁から狙ったのか
Did that shot come from the wall?!
Wh-Who fired that arrow?
だ…誰だ　今の矢を射たのは
At that distance? How?
あの距離で　どうやって
Hey!
Bring that man to me.
あの者を連れてまいりなさい
はっ　弓を射った者ですか
The one who fired the arrow, my lady?
We shall grant him a reward.
恩賞を与えましょう
Fire!
撃て
Forward!
進め　異教徒を殺せ
Kill the heathens!
神を畏れぬ愚か者どもに　鉄鎚を下すのだ
Deal a crushing blow to
these fools who do not fear God!
You damn pigs!
豚どもめ
Offer the corpses of these heathens to God!
異教徒の屍を神にささげよ
Death to the Devil's apostles!
悪魔の使徒どもに死を
そなた　名は
What is your name?
"Queen, Kingdom of Pars
Tahamenay"
I am called Gieve, my Lady Queen.
ギーヴと申します　王妃様
旅の楽士でございます
I am a traveling musician.
"Traveling Musician
Gieve"
I play the oud.
ウードを弾きます　笛も歌も詩も舞もいたします
I am also a flautist,
a singer, a poet, and a dancer.
And while I am at it, I will also add
ついでに申し上げておけば
that I wield the bow
and the sword and the spear
弓も剣も槍も　そこらの兵よりもうまく使います
better than your average soldier.
I have already seen your prowess with the bow.
そなたの弓の腕は　すでに見せてもらいました
I thank you for saving the
loyal Shapur from suffering.
忠実なシャプールを　苦しみから　救ってくれた礼を言います
では　殺人の罪は問わぬと仰せで
Then I will not be charged
with the crime of murder?
With all due respect, my Lady Queen,
that man is a terrible charlatan!
恐れながら　申し上げます　王妃様
その者は　とんでもない詐欺師です
What do you mean by that?
どういうことですか
"I am a prince of the Principality of Sistan
自分は　シースターン侯国の王子で
and I am traveling alone
across the lands for my training."
修業のため　一人で諸国を旅している…
That is what you told me just last night!
つい昨夜　あなたは私に　そう言ったではありませんか
I did.
言った
And now, you say that you are a musician?!
それが今　自分は楽士だと
So it was a lie that you are a prince?!
王子というのは　うそだったのですね
That was my dream
あれは俺の夢で
and you shared in my dream for one night.
お主はその夢を一夜俺と共有したのだよ
Hey, now, what is this?
おいおい　なんだ　これ
Such a precious, beautiful dream...
せっかくの麗しい夢
It is foolish to shred it
with the sword of ugly reality.
醜い現実の剣で切り裂くなど　愚かしい
If you had only accepted it,
お主さえ納得すれば
the dream would have become
a memory, growing ever sweeter,
夢は思い出となって　より甘美を増し
adding glamorous color to your life.
お主の人生を　あでやかに彩ろうものを
However, what I find eternally confounding
is just how weak the women of this world are
しかし　私めが不思議でならぬのは
世の女性たちがいかに王子という言葉に弱いかでございます
when it comes to the word "prince."
Truly, for a frivolous woman,
a frivolous dream is...
まこと浮薄なる女には浮薄なる夢が…
Your eloquence has been
made very clear to me.
そなたの能弁は　よく分かりました
Having come to this pass,
このうえは本来のそなたの職業について技を見せてもらうべきでしょうね
I believe we ought to have you
show us your skills in your true profession.
Now...
さて…
Then, to the heroes fighting to defend
the Royal Capital even as we speak,
では　今この瞬間も王都を守るために戦っておられる勇者たちのために…
I will dedicate the Heroic Deeds of Kaykhusraw.
カイ・ホスロー武勲詩抄をささげましょう
Upon the desolate plains of Māzangrān,
荒涼たる　マザングラーンの野に
Kaykhusraw's royal standard rippled.
カイ・ホスローの王旗　ひるがえれば
And evil Zahhāk's army fled in a frenzy
邪悪なるザッハークの軍勢は　逃げ惑いぬ
as a flock of sheep
frightened by spring thunder.
春雷におびえたる　羊の群のごとくに
The treasured sword Rukhnabad
that can cleave even steel
鉄をも両断せる　宝剣ルクナバードは
was forged of a piece of the sun.
太陽のかけらを鍛えたるなり
His beloved horse Rakhshna
possesses invisible wings.
愛馬ラクシュナには　見えざる翼あり
A fine steed surely worthy of the Jahangir.
ジャハーン・ギールにふさわしき　名馬ならん
There are not two suns in the heavens.
天空に太陽は　ふたつなく
地上にシャーオは　ただひとり
And there is but one shah upon the earth.
The hero with no equal, Kaykhusraw.
たぐいなき勇者カイ・ホスロー
With sword in hand, who will
succeed his mandate of Heaven?
剣もて　彼の天命を継ぐ者は　誰ぞ
That was magnificent.
見事でありました
One hundred pieces for your deed with the bow.
弓の技に１００枚　音楽に１００枚
One hundred pieces for your music.
Combined, I reward you
with two hundred pieces of gold.
合わせて金貨２００枚を　褒美に取らせます
How stingy.
しわいなぁ
I thought she would give me
at least five hundred pieces.
５００枚は　くれるものと思っていたのに
そなたが私の侍女を偽った罪の分は　差し引いてありますからね
A sum has already been deducted for your crime
of having misrepresented
yourself to my waiting woman.
Yes, my lady.
ははっ
Considering the distance from Atropatene,
アトロパテネからの　距離を考えれば
the Lusitanian army should already be
launching a full-scale attack on Ecbatana.
すでにルシタニア軍が　エクバターナに本格的な攻撃を始めている頃でしょう
The gates of Ecbatana are sturdy.
エクバターナの城門は　堅牢です
They cannot be breached with
flaming arrows or battering rams.
火矢をもってしても　破城鎚をもってしても　破れませぬ
However, there are no such
things as impregnable defenses.
しかし　この世に絶対の防御などというものは　ありません
No matter how sturdy they may be,
there are ways to breach them.
いかに堅牢といえど　破る方法はあります
For example...
例えば…
Are you speaking of opening them from within?
内側から開けるということか
Yes.
But opening the gates from within would be...
だが　内側から城門を開けることなど…
It is possible.
可能です
If I were leading the Lusitanian army,
もしも私がルシタニア軍の指導者であれば
I would open the gates, not with bows
and arrows or swords, but with words.
弓矢や剣よりも　言葉をもって門を開いてご覧に入れましょう
言葉で
With words?
If I wish to open the gates from within,
門の内側から開けようと思えば　内部に協力者がいればよいのです
all I need are confederates within!
エクバターナの中に　ルシタニア軍に協力する者など…
There are none within Ecbatana
who would aid the Lusitanian army...
No...
いや　いるかもしれない
There may be...
They are...
それは…
Slaves within the walls!
城内の奴隷たちよ
Rise up!
立ち上がれ
Seize your freedom!
自由を手に入れよ
お前たちを縛り搾取するパルスに
How long will you bow your heads to Pars,
いつまで頭を垂れているのか
who chain you and misuse you?!
--What are those bastards doing?
--All men are equal!
何やってるんだ　あいつら　大声上げて
Yelling like that...
さあ　蛮人どもの　考えることは理解できん
立ち上がれ
the way those savages think.
--Rise up! Seize your freedom!
自由を手に入れよ
This is bad.
まずいな
Slaves within the walls!
城内の奴隷たちよ
Under the God of Yaldabaoth, all men are equal!
イアルダボート神のもとに　万人は平等である
ルシタニアに協力する者には
Any who aid Lusitania
will be granted the rights of a free man
自由民の権利を　財産を与える
as well as riches and wealth!
Slaves! Overthrow your oppressors!
奴隷たちよ　圧政者を打倒せよ
Equal...
平等
Freedom...
自由
Oppressors...
圧政者
それは…
They are...
...the slaves!
奴隷たちだ
The azure crescent moon
wheels across the night sky
The glittering world transcends the clouds
With this journey's beginning that you dance now
Off into the yonder wishes go, drifting
When a tale that is shapeless
Spreads across the moonlight
The treasure that is within you
Melts away into the wind now
Tomorrow, try to take
wing as your unvarnished self
Sometime, somewhere,
you wanted this, remember?
You can hear it, can't you?
There; that shining dream from that day
The azure crescent moon
wheels across the night sky
The glittering world transcends the clouds
With this journey's beginning that you dance now
Off into the yonder wishes go
Oh, 'til this dream comes to an end
At the very least, the man in the silver mask
少なくとも銀仮面の男自身は
did not doubt that his was the righteous cause.
自分が正義であることを　疑ってはいなかった
Next time, "The Royal Capital Burns ~Part Two~."
"Chapter VI
The Royal Capital Burns ~Part Two~"
次回　王都炎上　後編
少年は　そして王となる
And thus, the boy would become king.